[Music]
I'm really delighted to see that we have
you know filled the entire house so
welcome one and all welcome to the this
iteration of the 2019 Provost's lecture
series and today we're thrilled to
welcome professor carl Freeston the
principal research fellow and scientific
director of the Wellcome Trust Center
for neural imaging as well as professor
at the institute of neurology at
University College London and a
consultant at the National Hospital for
neurology and neurosurgery in the United
Kingdom so this talk is sponsored not
only by the professor or the Provost's
office but it's also sponsored by the
Center for neural circuit dynamics at
Stony Brook University the Department of
Neurobiology and behavior as well as the
department of psychiatry at Stony Brook
University
so welcome Carl on behalf of all of us
and we're delighted to have you here
so the and as well we are welcomed by my
own organization the Institute for
Advanced computational science of which
I'm the student president and the ICS
the Institute for this you know advanced
computational science really tries hard
to make sure that we invite speakers
whose work touches on a wide variety of
perspectives and Carl really embodies
that that ethos so it's really hard to
define an area of research where Carl's
methods heaven influenced right so Carl
for example is the inventor of
statistical parametric mapping
voxel-based morphometry and dynamic
causal modeling okay
all motivated by schizophrenia research
based mathematical contributions include
variational laplacian procedures and
generalized filtering for hierarchical
Bayesian modeling version as well as
contributions in theoretical
neurobiology his most famous
contribution being the free-energy
principle for action and perception
which I expect will feature heavily in
today's talk okay professor christen
also holds honorary doctorates from the
universities of York Zurich and rad
Buddha University he's a member of the
academia europea a member of
the European molecular biology
organization the Royal Society the
Academy of Medical Sciences and he was
president of the International
Organization of human brain mapping he's
the recipient the first recipient of the
young investigators award in human brain
mapping he's a recipient of the Minerva
golden brain award we see the metal from
the collège de France received the
Wheldon memorial prize and medal in 2013
for contributions to mathematical
biology and it was the most recently he
was the 2016 recipient of the Charles
branch award for unparalleled
breakthroughs in brain research as well
as the glass brain award which is a
Lifetime Achievement Award in the field
of human brain mapping more recently
Tristan's work has been on the models of
functional integration in the human
brain in the principles that underlie
neuronal interactions so today we're
very happy to welcome here to talk about
this subject and more broadly on the
topic of I am therefore I think so
please join me in welcoming professor
well thank you for that lovely
introduction I told him he could say
three things about me and he thirty
things always a pleasure to hear them
though thank you there's also a great
pleasure to be here you you have one of
those beautiful parts of America I've
ever visited
you must be gorgeous working here I've
also enjoyed meeting hundreds of you I
have to say I'm absolutely worn out now
I've met so many interesting people
there are so many interesting things
have been asked so many difficult
questions that forgive me if my brain
starting to slow down for this lecture
this lecture is really a survey a back
story to a trend in the cognitive
neurosciences over the past decade or so
which is a move towards understanding
the brain as a statistic organ a
predictive processing machine so what I
want to do is just cast for you the main
elements of the back story as would be
articulated in the first half of a talk
by physicist and in the second half of
the talk by a neuroscientist and I'm
doing that because I am aware that I'm
speaking to a very eclectic and possibly
informed more informed than usual
audience so I will have equations in
case you're worried it's going to be two
back story issue so here's the the
overview of the talk I'm going to dis
discuss the properties that systems must
possess if they exist and by exists I
mean show some form of X distant
existential invariance of the soul we
associate with living systems I'm going
to illustrate and demystify some of
those principles using numerical
analysis simulations of a primordial
soup just to evolve a little creature
and ask some questions about the nature
of its behavior and how it
and then return to the point of view of
a neuroscientist and I'm going to tell
exactly the same story but this time as
a neurobiologist and talking about the
anatomy of inference bringing predictive
coding implementations of these
principles and how they might be
implemented by neural networks and then
finally if we have time and I got to get
a helpful hurry up sign from my host if
we run out of time I'm going to justify
the use of the quirky title I I am
therefore I think I think therefore
write out whichever you prefer so we're
going to make the final move which is
really rehearse in the same principles
but now under a prior belief that I am
the sort of creature that exists and
therefore must conform to these
principles and we'll conclude with
simulations of visual foraging and
epistemic affordance so let's start I'm
going to start with a question posed by
Schrodinger how can the events in space
and time which take place within the
spatial boundary of a living organism be
accounted for by physics and chemistry
I'm not going to answer that question
clearly but we'll pick up on the notion
of a spatial boundary and just note that
in order to talk about anything you need
to be able to demarcate or distinguish
disambiguate the thing from something
else or nothing and that really is the
role of the boundary that separates the
thing from the non thing and scrolling
would be the first person to acknowledge
that this boundary was in and of itself
a probabilistic stochastic quantity and
so I'm going to take that boundary to be
a Markov blanket so at this point I
normally ask to put your heart put your
hand up if you know what a Markov
blanket is good can you tell your
friends what a Markov blanket is
now you could have been clever a news
excuse you haven't got the microphone
for the recording but I think it's just
shyness and what he would have told you
what he would have said was that well
let's take this graphic here let's
assume that this is a description of
some little universe and all these
circles here denote states of any
abstract sort and the edges the arrows
denote a an influence of one state or
over another state and let's just take
some internal states of interest and the
Markov blanket comprises those other
states that in a statistical sense
insulate blanket render insula the
internal states from the external states
and by that I mean that if I wanted to
predict the internal state based upon
the rest of the universe I would only
ever need to know these blanket States
and technically they're defined in terms
of the parents the children and the
parents of the children of the internal
states of interest so a very simple
definition just in terms of conditional
dependencies or influences or some
adjacency matrix on this graph that
provides a set of states that separates
internal from external now only about 25
percent of you put your hand up and I
said what is a Markov blanket if I you
do all know what a Markov blanket is so
any of you that have worked with time
series or hidden Markov models and
Markovian processes have implicitly been
using the concept and know the concept
of a Markov blanket so if you just think
of these states being states of the
universe in time then the Markov blanket
is just the present moment in the sense
that everything I need to know about the
past that informs the future under a
Markovian assumption is in the present
so the present provides a Markov blanket
that statistically separates the past
from the future so that's all this means
all that we're doing here is
generalizing that notion to any our
basis arbitrary set of states that can
be articulated in two
of their dependencies and influences in
this forum here I'm going to make
another distinction which will become
important later on and I'm going to make
a bi partition of this set of states
here and into sensory states that are
not influenced by internal states and
active states that are not influenced by
external states and just to motivate
that distinction what I'm going to
invite you to do is just to think about
these conditional dependencies this
causal statistical architecture in the
context of things that we all know and
love and sometimes studied so these
blanket states comprise the active and
sensory states that separate external
from internal states and what I've done
here is just rewrite that graphic that
dependency graph in a form that you that
as a neuroscientist you recognize as a
cellular biologist you recognize where
we can associate the internal state and
every state of the brain there I'd need
to list in order to say this is a state
in the present moment all the synaptic
efficacy and activities and connection
strengths the active States could be the
states of all my muscles my autonomic
reflexes my motor system that cause
changes in the external states that
produce sensory impressions upon my
sensory states my cell 3 epithelium that
subsequently change my internal States
to induce changes in action and so the
cycle unfolds and I use the word cycle
deliberately here because what we have
is just a statistical statement of some
form of action perception or perception
action cycle exactly the same dependency
structure can be found at the cellular
level so we have all the intra cellular
states that could constitute a little
cell here we can associate say the
active space with the actin filaments
that support and provide motility to the
surface or sensory states of a cell with
receptors that are in receipt of
influences from the external meliha that
in turn affect the internal states that
affect the cell motility and this
structure just rests upon the absence
of two conditional dependencies that
define the active and the internal state
an absence of an influence of internal
states on the sensory states and an
absence of the influence of the external
states on the active States and that's
it that's all you need to define
something that can be separated from
something else so what and them to do
now is to ask you just to forget about
the Markov blanket for a moment what
we're going to do is just quickly run
through the dynamics of stuff that
exists and then what we're going to do
is to put the Markov blanket back in
play and see what interpretations follow
from the existence of a Markov blanket
under more generic principles of
self-organization so one of cartoon here
is a state space there's two states here
and we have some system say me and I
mean one state at any one particular
time and I trace out a trajectory or a
path through my state of my face space
here and as time unfolds I habitually
revisit or systematically revisit
neighborhoods of states that I have been
in before so you can think of this say
for example I'm getting up in the
morning I'm having my cup of coffee and
do my emails I do the morning work I
have lunch and so on this could be my
daily cycle or it could be my cardiac
cycle with systole and diastole as I
circulate around this attracting
sentence attracting manifold crucially
returning to the same state of being
periodically in a very itinerant way
this enormous ly complicated very
high-dimensional attracting set but it
must exist in the sense that I exist in
the sense that I have measurable states
that I keep on returning to define the
sort of system or the thing that I have
technically this would be a pull back or
around and dynamic attractor I'm just
going to refer to it as a set of
attracting of states that must be there
if something exists now the reason I'm
going on about that is that there's a
lot of machinery which we serve as we'll
know and love that is apt for describing
some of the fundamental dynamic
so that must be a play if this
attracting set is in plane so here I've
just written down the long-run
description of this system in terms of
motion which is equal to flow dependence
upon States but some random fluctuations
Omega I can describe not just the flow
on this attracting set but interpret
this flow in terms of the probability
that I would be in this state if I was
sampled at random at a random time in
terms of a probability density and I'm
going to associated that probability
density with the the sorts of states
that I'm in when I have attained or
settled down to my crafting set when I
am in non-equilibrium steady state and
if I do that that means that this
probability the probability of being in
a particular state given me is described
by the density dynamics ready to change
the probability of my States given me
and I can write that down using the
fokker-planck equation the master
equation the congrats forward equation
whatever you want to describe this
interestingly it will transpire also to
be this floating away the equation and I
can write it down as a function of the
amplitude of the random fluctuations and
the gradients of this and the flow and
the probability distribution if you
don't know what this means don't worry
about it it's just something that has to
apply if this attracting set or not non
equilibrium steady state exists the key
thing about it is that I know but once I
settle down this is zero and if this is
zero that now allows me to write down
the flow as a function of the
probability the gradients of the log
probabilities of states of being that I
am typically in given the amplitude of
the random fluctuations and a solenoid l
component here Q which is anti-symmetric
matrix so this is gonna be quite crucial
it's basically as if I exist my dynamics
my flow must satisfy this equation and
this equation is a functional or a
function of a log probability we
is just the sorts of states that
characterized me for those of you who
don't know this formalism I'll just very
quickly go through in a mock in a more
intuitive fashion imagine that I place a
drop of ink in a cup of water and due to
the random thermal fluctuations the
molecules of that ink will disperse them
cells throughout the solvent so I would
expect to see for a system that wasn't
going to attain any form of steady state
equilibrium or otherwise the ink diffuse
until the concentration is uniform
everywhere in the solvent that is not
the characteristic of the systems that
are interesting as what we are talking
about the systems that do this I drop
the water in it and then it seems to the
oil ink and it seems to gather itself up
so attains its non equilibrium
self-assembly as if the molecules are
flowing up probability gradients so I
can reverse diffusion and it is exactly
that particular dynamics that that
solution to the fokker-planck equation
describes so if we associate the
concentration of the ink molecules with
the probability distribution then what
we're saying is we can understand these
two components of the flow as basically
this gradient flow climbing up
probability or concentration gradients
and this solenoid 'el or divergence free
flow as flowing around the ISO contours
here and it's in particular this
gradient flow that I want to drill down
it is there in order to exactly balance
the dispersion of the random
fluctuations so I'm not talking about
detailed balance I'm talking about
something much more general that if I
have attained non equilibrium steady
state and I exist in that sense then it
must be that on average my flow is
exactly countering the dispersion of my
non-equilibrium statistical T
distribution so that's good is it
interesting it is very interesting
as a lightly the godfather of most of
physics so that solution and in
particular the fokker-planck equation
under right so you can coerce it to
underwrite classical mechanics and
quantum mechanics so for example we can
set the amplitude of those random
fluctuations to zero and what falls out
of that solenoidal flow because the
gamma part of the gradient flow has gone
away is just classical Lagrangian
mechanics and Newtonian laws we can go
to the other end of the scale and ignore
the solenoidal bits and just focus on
the random fluctuation and all the
interesting behaviors that one gets from
random fluctuations that do not cannot
see these probability gradients they
just pass through potential barriers for
example and then what we get from that
is basically a a formulation that ends
up with things like the fluctuation
theorems modulation dissipation theorem
and stochastic or for ensemble
statistical mechanics we can just look
at the square root complex square root
of that non equilibrium state density
and treat that as a wave function and
then the fokker-planck equation writes
itself as a as a spur dinner equation
what we're going to do though is
consider another sort of mechanics that
resps explicitly on the Markov blanket
so that's the move here we're just
taking standard physics and saying what
would it look like if there was always a
Markov blanket there and that brings
some interesting things to the table
first of all it means that there are two
sets of dynamics dynamics that pertain
to the internal states and the active
States that look as if they're doing
gradient flows and they have a purpose
and furthermore we're going to interpret
a bound on the thing that they are
flowing on in terms of a variation free
energy so that's the basic story I'm
just foreshadowing or for grounding that
story as an extension the entirely
consistent with and complementary to
things that we are be taught at school
so that's our gradient flow the solution
to the fokker-planck equation and this
is the same solution but now just
written down in terms of the states of a
particle we're assuming that a particle
comprises the internal States and it's
Markov blanket that has active and
sensory states and I'm focusing on the
active States here and because of those
Independence's I only only need to
concentrate on the probability of the
blanket States the sensory inactive
states so this is a solution to this
non-equilibrium steady state there must
be they're describing the flow of
internal and active States and the
interesting thing here is the both look
as if they're trying to optimize or
maximize the same quantity and that's
the log the gradient of the log
probability of the blanket States given
the system me in question and the story
is going to be basically that we can
look at the this mechanics as perception
and the flow of active States in terms
of action and what licenses me to say
that well just the form of that equation
makes a lot of sense from the point of
view of many many different perspectives
in psychology and the life sciences so
I'll just briefly run through a few of
them just and you will know this stuff
for at least one or two of these things
this just so you can see how I've joined
the dots from the point of view of
motivating the central importance of
this long probability up here so we've
just said that these describe attracting
States so the greater the probability of
being in any attracting state or blanket
state here means those are the sorts of
states that I've attracted to that I
will be typically found in basically
they can be construed as having value
for me the things that I aspire to or
they're attract me and what we're saying
is basically that both perception and
action are in the game of maximizing
value and on that reading we can spin
out things like reinforcement learning
control theory until if we're doing
economics it could even be expected
utility theory that's nice because the
negative of this value is known as self
information and information theory
tribus call it surprisal I'm just gonna
refer to it as a surprise it's as the
empower bility of a negative log
probability of being in some state
incidentally that's the quantity that's
going to be upper bounded by the free
energy so I'm going to use free energy
synonymously really with this surprisal
or surprise so what this says is the
systems that possess a Markov blanket
and have attained non equilibrium steady
state are basically trying to get and
put an upper bound on surprise and from
that we can understand things like the
informatics principle principles a
minimum redundancy and indeed the
variational free energy principle that
we're going to be talking about that's
nice because this thing here when taken
in expectation or the average of this
over time or over the path is entropy so
what we're saying is that this dual
minimization of this quantity here this
surprisal is just a statement of
self-organization it's putting an upper
bound on the dispersion or the entropy
of the disorder of me and that's how you
might understand it as a physicist or
from the point of view of synergetics
because if you're a physiologist it's
just a statement of homeostasis that's
all we're saying we're just saying that
systems are persevering juror and a
changing world are those that keep their
physiological states within viable
bounds they gather themselves up and
place bounds upon that dispersion the
final interpretation which is the one
that I want to leave region is from the
point of view of a statistician
this probability here is it's the
probability of some sensory or blanket
data condition now not upon me but if I
treat me as a model of those data this
now becomes something called model
evidence or marginal likelihood and it
is the holy grail in terms of the
quantity that you want to optimize when
doing Bayesian inference and if we take
that interpretation then we what we are
saying is that this is equivalent to say
that we can understand said the brain
did this is a Bayesian brain we'd
understand that in terms of evidence
accumulation and indeed predictive
coding and that's the sort of story that
I'm going to try and to tell you for the
remainder of the talk before I do so
that is I promise you that I try and
demystify some of the behavior entailed
by that formulation a non-equilibrium
steady-state using simulations so here
the simulations what I've done here is
take a hundred and so if a macromolecule
synthetic macromolecules equipped them
with autonomous dynamics I like a little
creating a little acted super acted
matter and then coupled them with strong
and weak forces strong repulsive forces
and depend upon the spatial distance and
weak electrochemical coupling here and
just let them self-organized and fall
settle down onto their attracting set
and once I've done that I've created a
little universe where crucially I know
all those dependencies and I know all of
the dependencies that would otherwise
define on that would define the Markov
blanket so I can now go in there and
search for the Markov blanket and ask is
there a little creature living in the
middle of this little soup and if I
identified this the eight most connected
states
I can then using the dependences
incredible adjacency matrix a find that
parents the children and the parents and
the children and identify this little
synthetic creature with its internal
states encoded in blue the active states
surrounding it encoded in red that
support the sensory states of magenta
that then separate the internal states
and external state since I on and it
sits there happily whittling away
wagging its tail could be like a little
there cilium here
now I've simulated that thing that has a
Markov blanket I can now ask well is
that self that Bayesian interpretation
of the dynamics that must be there given
is now settled down to non equilibrium
steady state is that a viable
description of the behavior of this
little synthetic creature so in other
words are there any attributes or states
of the configurations of internal states
that in some sense model or predict the
states on the outside and it's very
simple to show that yes indeed that has
to be the case as is the case so here's
our a numerical example of that what
I've done here is just taken a mixture
of time lagged internal electrochemical
States and ask what mixture best
predicts some mixture or some motion
physical motion of the external states
and these are the internal states and
here in the solid line is a prediction
and the dotted line is the actual
velocity of these external states so if
you're a you're a scientist you can
imagine this is a simulated visual
motion experiment you know are there any
internal electrochemical fluctuations
that predict or are predicted by changes
in visual motion out there that I cannot
access directly but I can do through my
sensory epithelium my retina and you can
see that not only is our correlation but
you can actually pick up events and even
see them in terms of the internal
fluctuations here is highlighted by the
white arrow
the reason I've shown this example is if
you look closely you can see that the
internal States actually predate this
rapid expulsion of this external state a
little bit like a solar flare and then
it's pulled back again so the internal
states are not really seeing the
external states it looks as if they may
also cause in terms of temporal
precedents the external states that may
be causing the internal state so the
question is what's causing what let me
ask a quest
let me pose others question you know the
internal space causing the external
states or the external states causing
the internal states what it is very much
a tricular leg we do which side do you
want to come down the very fat you're
teasing me with a flippant answer means
you know the right answer which of
course neither it's good this is this is
just an instance of what Huygens noted
centuries ago of generalised
synchronization or chaos our generalized
synchrony so this is the story where you
have old-fashioned clocks that you are
suspended from the same wall or the same
beam and inevitably they're attracting
sej requires them to be on the same
synchronization money fell so they will
eventually come to swing in synchrony
inevitably and that's all that we're
seeing here we're just seeing a
completely symmetrical synchronization
of dynamics in virtue of them both the
outside and the inside being conditioned
upon the Markov blanket it can be no
other way which is an interesting
picture so in fact this is a picture
that he actually drew of his two clocks
with the beam here so from our point of
view one clock would be the internal
states these cover the external space
and the beam is the constituting the
blanket States and one interesting
aspect of this is it shows you the
symmetry of the mathematical argument
here so we I have had an interesting
conversation this afternoon what this
symmetry means and what it means is if
you subscribe to the view that the
dynamics here are all about inferring
what's going on over here
then the converse has to be true that
means that the environment is trying to
infer and to learn about you as much as
you are trying to learn about the
environment and our conversation went
right through to evolution and eco niche
construction so it's not a silly view
and it's certainly a mathematical truism
anyway so that's all the heavy lifting
that's all the hard part done
just to summarize what we said so far
the existence of a Markov blanket
necessarily implies a partition of
states into internal states their
blanket sensory inactive states an
external or hidden states hidden behind
the blanket and because active states
change but are not changed by external
states they minimize the entropy of the
internal states and their blanket and
this means an action will appear to
maintain the structural and functional
integrity of the blanket and some people
have written about that in terms of auto
police's or self-assembly unlike
internal states appear to infer the
hidden causes of sensory states by
maximizing Bayesian model evidence and
influence those cause causes through
action and I'm going to refer to that as
active inference so just different takes
or losses on something that is
necessarily there if you exist and you
have a Markov blanket no I've forgotten
about this is something that one of my
visiting research fellow said me not
last weekend the weekend before so for
those of you who think the Markov
blanket is some abstract mathematical
constant it is not you can buy them in
America so this is this is Frances
little baby Kira to two months since two
weeks old now and this is what his wife
bought him so that's actually Markov
circuit 1858 I think keeping her states
warm as she makes her own inferences
okay so as promised what I'm going to do
now is just rehearse but using a
different rhetoric this same story as if
I were giving a lecture or talking to
neuroscientists and I'm going to now say
well what this means or what it would
look like is the things that have brains
will appear to be little constructive
organs statistical organs that will all
be always appear to trying to infer
predict model what's going on beyond
their sensorium and this is beautifully
illustrated by this it's yeah 16th
century oil painter who was known for
painting still lines that when viewed
from another perspective have a very
different interpretation you immediately
have a very different hypothesis about
what caused that particular pattern of
sensory input so if you now see a face
there where you didn't before the key
thing is you made that that face was on
the inside so the argument here in
contrast sort of 20th century view of
perceptual synthesis and in particular
some visual inference is it it is not an
outside-in process it is not as a series
of clever filters or extraction devices
it's very much an inside-out process
that you have a hypothesis that's in
there and you submit that hypothesis to
the sensory evidence and then reject or
accept that hypothesis if you can
predict what's going on that's the basic
idea it's a sort of strange inversion of
a Denon like sort of 20th century
thinking about perception so it's a much
more constructivist one that speaks to
this little circular causality that was
seen from the physical perspective so
this idea is not new you can trace it
back to the students of Plato
so here are some of my favorite
intellectual architects of this style of
thinking probably best articulated by
Helmholtz so for example objects are
always imagined as being present in the
field of vision as would have to be
there in order to produce the same
impression on the nervous mechanism so
again what he's saying is you have to
have the hypothesis the model the
internal dynamics that would be able to
predict what I would see if that was
actually out
otherwise you can't perceive it and this
of course is very closely related to
Richard Gregory's notion of perception
as I pollicis testing then literally we
palpate the world and we'll see an
example this in the final slide with our
eyes we visually palpate in the world to
garner gather evidence that confirms or
disconfirms our beliefs about what's out
there causing our sensory impressions
and these ideas have been taken the use
of great effect by people in machine
learning Geoffrey Hinton and Peter Diane
came up with the Helmholtz machine and
borrowed the notion of variational Bayes
operation free energy minimization
developed by Richard Feynman quantum
mechanics in the setting of a sort of
Bayesian formulation of probability
theory do you use these ideas that are
still being used in various incarnations
for example variational autoencoders in
deep learning to great effect in terms
of inferring on classifying and
recognizing let's go back to Helmholtz
and the notion of the the notion of an
impression on the nervous system so for
us that's this basically this sort of
sensory impression on our sensory
blanket or a sensory veil so if this
infants perspective is right what this
means is that we have to explain how our
brains can take these sensory
impressions and from them derive an
explanation as to what course and so
what's behind what's hidden behind this
sensory blanket and of course the Amazon
we've already got the answer it's just
the solution to the complaint equation
so what would that look like if you were
a neuroscientist well I've actually
written it down in a way that you'd
recognize if you're an engineer doing
time series analysis here so what I've
done is written down this gradient flow
that we've established as the solution
to the the non-equilibrium steady state
I've just swapped out the log
probability with this free energy bound
on the low probability that we don't
need to worry about that at the
so now we're doing a gradient flow on
the variation free energy and if it's
rewritten these two gradient and
solenoidal components in terms of a
divergence free update where mu now
stands in for the internal states and
are rewritten the free energy here in
terms of prediction error weighted by
their precision on the squared
prediction error weighted by their
inverse variance or prediction here now
the result done that is that that is a
Kalman filter where the precision now
plays the role of a Kalman gain and the
way that these things work is that they
gather evidence to infer the hidden
states of the causes of sense data based
upon a prediction given what they
believe there so their expectations so
let's take view now the internal states
to encode a belief namely the
expectation about what will happen next
so this is a derivative operator so now
describing the change in the states and
an update term based upon a prediction
error now what is a prediction error
well let's just say we have this sensory
impression here this shadow and we have
this hypothesis encoded by our internal
expectation say neuronal activity that
it was caused by a howling dog and if I
had a model or a journey of mapping
between my expectation of the causes and
the sensory consequences of that cause
say gee to generate the consequences
from the causes I could simply compare
my predictions with what I'm actually
sensing to generate a prediction error
and that means that we can understand
this gradient flow that must be there in
terms of updating my expectations to
minimize prediction error and if I can
do that successfully
I always then have an adequate
explanation for my sensorial crucially
it doesn't actually have to be the
correct explanation so it might not be a
dog but I will never know that and I
never need to know that provided I could
always keep my prediction error so my
explanation for the world is perfectly
or sufficiently good provided I can
always get the prediction error
precision where two prediction error
minimize or upper bounded or minimize
the generalization that which is this
variational free-energy that itself is
abound upon this surprising or self
information so that's the basic idea
it's nice because it provides its simple
perspective on the intimate relationship
between action and perception if
everything is in the game of minimizing
prediction error then there are we have
a nice way of understanding the two
complimentary ways in which we can do
that first of all we can change our
predictions to make them more like the
sensory impressions and we can think of
that as belief updating in the brain to
improve our predictions to minimize the
prediction error and any perception by
changing predictions but there's another
way of doing it we can make the
sensations that we sample more like our
predictions so we can actually act upon
the world to go and literally palpate it
in a way that selectively samples those
sensory outcomes that we predicted a
priori and it turns out that that looks
exactly like classical reflex arcs both
in motor control theory and also in
other in terms of autonomic reflexes
basically a servo that is provided with
a neat like a thermostat just provided
with a prediction it's setpoint and then
all the peripheral machinery the action
is just in the service of changing the
world bring the temperature back down to
the setpoint just minimizing that
precision weighted prediction error and
that's basically we're going to try and
illustrate in the final few slides and
first of all just to say if this is
going to work then we have to make
realistic
predictions of our sensory impressions
and clearly the sorts of impressions
that we are subject to are deeply
structured very dynamic which means that
our garroted models that are used to
generate these predictions to form the
prediction error are going to have to be
in turn deeply structured basically deep
models but also dynamic they're going to
be deep dynamic
your models and clearly that's a nice to
hear if you're a neurobiologist because
that's exactly how the brain is
organized certainly it hits you in the
face if you look at the visual system so
I just khartoum that here so we have
these two hypotheses or causes if we
wanted to predict some retinal sensory
data here you know what am I looking at
and where am I
palpating it and I put these two causes
together and I'd cascade them down
ultimately to make some predictions
about the sensory flow that would
actually be sampled if these
explanations were correct
so here the generative process these
causes cascading down here to produce
sensory states at the center of the
Markov blanket plus the random
fluctuations at each point so what would
an inference machine what would
self-organization non-equilibrium State
look like based upon this architecture
well it would just have the form of our
gradient flow and when I write that down
and swap out the way in which these
sensory states were generated with the
prediction errors and the predictions or
expectations here what we get is a
message passing scheme that looks very
much like what we see in the rail brain
so the random fluctuations have now been
replaced by prediction errors and the
causes or experience states are being
replaced by expectations about those
hidden states and they still cascade
down but they do so via the prediction
errors that crucially now are returned
back up to update and inform the
expectations using this gradient flow or
Kalman filter or predictive coding
equation here so the picture that falls
out for free from that gradient flow
interpretation of non-equilibrium
self-organization - steady state is
exactly what we see in the brain this
counter stream of ascending prediction
errors that induce belief updating or
base and belief updating to provide
better explanations that can be returned
by descending predictions - prediction
error cells so there are self cancelling
through this recurrent message
passing that is hierarchically composed
or arranged here's a quick example for
the visual system just to sort of put
action back into into the story so
imagine we have some visual retinal
information coming in here against the
lateral geniculate nucleus it's in
receipt of top-down predictions from the
visual cortex and they are partially
good but not completely so there's a
prediction error that gets passed up as
the news where the information that has
yet to be explained that excites changes
in the expectations in the visual cortex
but crucially these expectations are
themselves being predicted by a high
level so that's the secondary prediction
error and that's passed up and so on so
on to increasingly a hierarchical depth
until you've minimized prediction error
all levels in the hierarchy and you have
a set of expectations and different
levels of coarse graining in space and
in time
that provides an account of your
sensorial of multiple levels of
abstraction I've also put in here
there's another sort of sensory
information from the sensory states of
the Markov bank at the proprioceptive
input the status of my muscles my
oculomotor system now these could come
in they could be in receipt of top-down
predictions and I could change my mind
about where I am looking but here's
where the reflex comes in this is where
action comes in there's another way in
which these particular prediction errors
can be minimized and that's if they
couple straight back to the outside
world through the active States so all
that means is if I register there's a
difference between my sensed stretch of
my muscle and my predictive stretch of
the muscle then I will contract or relax
the muscle until the sensations match
the predictions so what I've just
described as a classic thank you a
classical reflex arc and we can use that
to simulate all sorts of things I'll
just give you one example really to
illustrate the difference between this
example and the interesting thing which
justifies the title of this talk in
couple of minutes we've just used that
hill-climbing equation with a particular
generative model to emulate or simulate
slow person tracking I won't go into the
matter FATA carcasses of on substitution
area don't need to know how this simple
Newtonian mechanics are described an
interesting model where I believe that
the same things that pull a target
around are also pulling my eyeball so
we've written into this particular
simulated subject or synthetic agent the
prior belief in their charity model that
causes predictions of both what they see
and what they feel from their eye
movements the belief that there's some
fictive invisible point of attraction
out there there is pulling a target
around and is also pulling their center
of gaze and if the agent believes this
is the best explanation for its sensory
world then it will fulfill those
predictions by tracking and also
anticipating the location of the target
and which is very very realistic slope
assume target movements realistic to the
extent that you can simulate occlusion
so this is just a simulation here with a
sinusoidal target here that goes behind
an occluder here and then we're looking
at the beliefs of this simulated agent
during the periods of occlusion denoted
by the gray bars here and in particular
what would happen if I changed the
precision of the gain or the confidence
or afforded their prediction errors
would it make the sorts of mistakes that
people with schizophrenia make and
indeed it does and you can simulate both
the psychophysics and also the the the
tracking of the target in the slope soup
paradigm to emulate very very precisely
and in detail the sorts of slow passing
deficits you get from a lesion of this
active inference formulation of how we
sample our world I don't want to talk
about this is what I want to talk about
in
in the last couple of minutes I want to
talk about active inference and
epistemic affordance so I'm going to
make the final move now which is taking
us to a more abstract application of
these ideas where I'm going beyond just
saying I have beliefs about the world
and I'm going to act upon the world to
make those beliefs come true by vibe
minimizing my prediction error I'm going
to say that my journey immoral now
entertains the consequences of acting in
the future and furthermore I believe
that I am the sort of creature that will
act as if I have I am minimizing the
free energy that will ensue or the
prediction errors that will ensue if I
did this all that and I'm now going to
select from one policy or another
policies purely in the service of
minimizing this free energy bound on
surprisal if I were talking to
philosophers what we're saying is
basically if I act I must have beliefs
about the consequences of action so if I
have posterior beliefs about action I
must have pry beliefs about action and
therefore it follows that what are those
Prai believe well if I am a self
evidencing creature in other words if I
try to maximize my model evidence
therefore I believe I behave as if I am
a self evidencing creature which
technically means that I will select
those actions that minimize expected
surprise or self information I free
energy consequent upon an action so very
briefly what happens is that you set up
a bunch of policies actions like where
to look next and then you work out
technically using the posterior
predictive density over the outcomes if
I did that the free energy that you
would have got if you write that down it
actually transpires that it has very
intimate relationships with a lot of
extant approaches to planning and
ultimate control and an economics so the
expected free energy has these two bits
to it it's expectation over posted
predictive density of the sensory
outcomes here's the normal here's the
evidence bit and here's a cow
divergence so I'm going to demonstrate
that basically in the context of just
choosing where to look next that's
that's basically my space of policies
that I have to select from so what I'm
going to be doing is selecting the place
to look next that max minimizes my
expected free energy what does that mean
it's basically minimizing expected
surprise which means and minimizing
uncertainty which means maximizing
information gain reducing as much
uncertainty as I can by selecting those
epistemic lis rich sensory or what I
believe will be an aesthetically rich
parts of the world that will reduce as
much uncertainty as possible about about
what I think is causing it and indeed if
you compute this sort of expected free
energy create salience map so we've
actually referred to this expected free
energy or an important component of it
as salience it's also known as Bayesian
surprise this was just making the point
that we can actually go into this
expected free energy expression and just
focus in on various mixtures of its
terms and pull out stuff which has been
in literature for decades so if I ignore
the pragmatic or the prior bleeds my pry
preferences I have no preference about
what I'm going to see then what is left
is earth what atiim Baldy will call
basin surprise what Horace baller would
call mutual information so if I take it
preferences out out of the game then I
end up with basically an info max or
minimum redundancy principle but it
still is only part of the story I can
put the Preferences back in but I can
retain uncertainty about the outcomes of
action and then I get risk sensitive
control of people optimal control theory
use where they minimize the divergence
between preferred sensations or outcomes
and those that I predict under a
particular outcome so if you're an
economist this would also be
resuscitated choice behavior in
economics and I can take the final sort
of uncertainty out and I can actually
just get back to expected utility theory
or enforcement learning so I take all
sorts uncertainty off the table both in
terms of what would happen if I did that
and my uncertainty about the state of
the world we get back to
good old-fashioned reinforcement
learning and expected utility theory and
this is the final slide that just shows
you the solutions to this gradient flow
with a particular Journal to model where
it's just trying to resolve uncertainty
about the causes of these sensations
these four build samplings that you're
seeing here under the hypothesis that
could be an upright phase a side of a
face or an inverted face and how it's
choosing by appeal to the 6:53 energy or
salience map the best bits of the image
to look at to resolve as much
uncertainty as it can so there were a
few moves it's pretty certainly wasn't a
bright face and indeed it was an upright
face so I will conclude by giving the
last word as always to Helmholtz who
basically said what I've just said that
said in one sentence each movement we
make by which we alter the the
appearance of objects should be thought
of as an experiment designed to test
whether we have understood correctly the
invent relations of the phenomena before
us that is their existence in definite
spatial relations and with that I just
want to thank all the people whose ideas
I've been talking about and of course
thank you for your attention thank you
very much indeed
[Applause]
questions are you
well it's a nice gentle question not
very excitement is the word worry is
more and it's usually worried about
their gender the people I supervise so
at the moment the it seems to be taken
towards natural language processing and
natural language understanding that the
people I work with a cognitive
neuroscientist centered in speech and
noise and and hearing and recovery of
language function following stroke on
the other side of the coin there are
people who want to see if these ideas
scale up in a commercial setting so
they're going off trying to you know get
funding for startups and the likes of
that that agender is really finding toy
proofs of principle where you get these
sorts of schemes outperforming deep
learning and open G open AI gym formats
and the like so that's that's not
exciting but it's worrying I think so I
should also say a large number of my
younger colleagues or also come from
ecology and ethology and theoretical
biology so they've taken these ideas and
made them work in the context of eco
nation construction and mathematical
modeling of sort of not selection but
the sorts of processes you'd see in new
wave evolutionary psychology and deal
where the cultures come in and how does
this bootstrapping to in the inside and
the outside States where the outside
states are other creatures like me get
into the game of making the world much
more predictable and learn and also that
that's also very interesting and I've
mentioned already some people might 11
at Tufts is taking these ideas and
seeing if we can use them to explain
games and dances and self-organization
active inference at the level of cells
and whether that is an explanation for
pattern formation in terms of
morphogenesis and possibly in the
context of near plays or in cancer so
there are lots of exciting applications
very P bases that were just worries as a
basis of excitement with whether we can
keep up or
but I think
we will order more
yes yes oh well
it lives center stage you know so this
notion of epistemic affordance that you
get from these simulations where this is
just about leave appalling this is
basically what would happen if I did if
I did that this I think is one of the
most beautiful expressions of this
imperative to reduce uncertainty
so remember mathematically free energy
upper bound surprised and expected
surprise is uncertainty is entropy so
all that we are saying here is that we
are things that act to minimize
uncertainty now one of the best ways to
act to minimize uncertainties to see
what happened if I did that so when you
look at the posterior beliefs over the
consequences of action what would happen
if I pull that lever that becomes
incredibly attractive from the point
you're in the jargon of Gibsonia people
the the in activist movement it has
epistemic affordance so this Bayesian
surprised or this this mutual
information if you're Horace Barlow I
think that's probably more easily
understood as this this intense
epistemic affordance or attractiveness
so the yellow lever also they believe in
the Yellow Submarine if it has not been
pulled before all other things being
equal is the most has the greatest
affordance to because it's novel so when
you rewrite this base and surprise not
in terms of posterior beliefs about
states of the world but personally I
believe it's about continues that the
parameters that generate states in the
world the consequences of action that
looks exactly like novelty so that
question I think is a great question on
two levels first of all it allows me
just to sort of D technical eyes the
basic imperative and we're talking about
it's just about sampling salient stuff
be just novelty
seeking but on another level you're
absolutely right as well that you know
these imperatives do describe people and
particular scientists you know this is
just the you know describing exactly
what we do always spend our entire lives
doing is generating hypotheses carefully
designing these experiments with
epistemic affordance to disclose and
reveal the most evidence that we can and
if we could scientists we make these
good every stomach moves and if we're
not we don't get funding and we confirm
our own ideas or get ignored so really
this is that this is another way of
disarticulated the the notion of the the
brain as a scientist you know the both
subject exactly the same the same the
same notions
and that's a tricky question to answer
in terms of normally I would have a
simulation to show you how it works
reproduction here is is one way of if
you like a particular class of having
these attendant attracting sets so one
level from the point of view of a
species over a certain period of time
before after the speciation occurred to
create that species you can write down
the trajectory of the species where each
of those cycles I was protecting before
as my daily life cycle or my heartbeat
that could actually be over better than
an evolutionary time scale so you can
look at that as you know that as
revisiting certain states of being over
somatic time like being an embryo being
and as I go being an infant and go
through a neurodevelopmental cycle so
the key question there is do the same
mechanics apply at the level of
evolution that must be in play if there
is an attracting set that is a species
and that leads us into the game of now
reinterpreting the price equation or the
replicator dynamics that are used to
model evolution not so much specifically
it as a reproduction but certainly in
terms of you know evolutionary theory
more generally as basically a process of
inference and that's very interesting
because there are a lot of there's a lot
of mathematically the answer is yes
absolutely and I think that chuckle yes
Frank has written about that and John
Campbell talking about Universal
Darwinism it's a truism that the
population dynamics that are used to
model theoretical evolution are just
Kalman filters they are just variational
free energy minimizing great gradient
flows the more interesting thing I think
is the the memes and the rhetoric you
can put on top of that so now if that is
true it means a natural selection now
becomes Bayesian model selection and now
beliefs become or internal states now
become phenotypes so the phenotype now
becomes if you like
a statement of belief about what sorts
of things are fit for purpose in this
eco nation and the Bayesian model alert
selection now does a structure learning
of the phenotype where you've actually
got explicitly an ensemble density
encoding the posterior belief so
evolution now becomes a scientist so
evolution now does its belief updating
using a sample density over the
phenotypes that constitute the
population density that conforms to
exactly the same rules that I the
fokker-planck equation describes so I
think it's a lovely game to be played in
terms of theoretical biology just
unpacking the same maths that you might
use to describe you know it's creating a
wave equation but applying it to
population dynamics and just see what
you mean when you talk about natural
selection and how that means relates to
things like structure learning it's a
natural language processing for example
example mathematically they all have the
same form that was a bit of a hand wavy
answer at the level of reproductions the
reproductions an interesting one because
it implies a splitting of the genotype
and that's that I think requires some
finer or more detailed analysis